how to use sound_font_riper for GBA FE

Using the Windows command prompt (cmd.exe), navigate to the folder containing sound_font_riper.exe and a copy of your rom.
Use this command:

sound_font_riper -s[FREQ] [IN].gba [OUT].sf2 [ADDRESS]

Replace [FREQ] with whatever is the sampling rate of your drums (or other fixed frequency samples). Unless you've change the byte at
$d06f4 (FE8U) to use a new sampling rate, this will be 13379.
Replace [IN] with the filename of your rom and [OUT] with whatever you want to call the newly-created soundfont.
Replace [ADDRESS] with the address of the voice table you want to convert into a soundfont. To easily find this, add
"MESSAGE Voice table begins at CURRENTOFFSET" to your music installer right before your first voice table entry and EA will tell
you exactly where the table is being written when you assemble the buildfile.

Make sure to add your soundfont in the VirtualMidiSynth configuration window so you can use it in your music editing app of choice.
Personally, I like to keep all of my soundfonts in one folder, but if you have a lot of songs that get their own voice table (i.e. their own
soundfont), you may want to keep all your project's soundfonts in their own folder in the music folder.